A Finding Aid to the Edith Emerson Papers, 1839-1981, bulk 1894-1971, in the Archives of American Art AAA.emeredit
Archives of American Art
Edith Emerson papers
bulk 1894-1971
1839-1981
AAA.emeredit
Archives of American Art
2.1 Linear feet
The papers of painter, illustrator, and curator Edith Emerson measure 2.1 linear feet and date from 1839 to 1981, with the bulk of the material dating from 1894-1971. Found within the papers are biographical material; letters from friends and colleagues; writings and notes by Emerson and others; artwork, including three sketchbooks; subject files; photographs of Emerson, family, friends, and artwork; and scattered printed material.
Emerson, Edith, 1888-1981
Separated Materials note
Edith Emerson lent four scrapbooks for microfilming in 1977. Loaned material is available on microfilm reels 1186-1187, but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Papers were donated in 1990 by the Free Library of Philadelphia, who received them from Emerson.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1950s (Box 1; 1 Folder)
Series 2: Letters, 1916-1965 (Box 1, OV 3; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1887-1970 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Artwork, 1839, 1882-1954 (Box 1, OV 3; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Subject Files, circa 1865-1955 (Box 1-2; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1900-1971 (Box 2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Material, circa 1916-1981 (Box 2, 6 folders)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter, illustrator, and curator Edith Emerson measure 2.1 linear feet and date from 1839 to 1981, with the bulk of the material dating from 1894-1971. Found within the papers are biographical material; letters from friends and colleagues; writings and notes by Emerson and others; artwork, including three sketchbooks; subject files; photographs of Emerson, family, friends, and artwork; and scattered printed material.
Biographical/Historical note
Edith Emerson (1888-1981) was a painter, illustrator, and curator in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
Born in Oxford, Ohio, Emerson studied at the Art Institute of Chicago with John Vanderpoel and Thomas Wood Stevens and at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts with Cecilia Beaux, Violet Oakley, and Daniel Garber. She assisted Violet Oakley primarily between 1917 and 1930 and shared her studio from 1918 until Oakley's death in 1961. Emerson served on the Board of Directors of the Woodmere Art Gallery beginning in 1940, subsequently becoming Curator. She was also a founding member of the Violet Oakley Memorial Foundation.
Curators--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Illustrators -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Painters -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Women artists
- Biographical Material, circa 1950s; Series 1; 1 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains two pages of typewritten biographical material about Edith Emerson, with a few handwritten annotations.
  - Biographical Summaries, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters, 1916-1965; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, OV 3
  Arrangement note
  Letters are arranged in chronological order.
  Within this series are personal and business letters. Included are letters between Edith Emerson and friends, as well as prospective clients for her artwork. Of note are letters from Margaret French Cresson, Elizabeth Shippen Green Elliott, Daniel Garber, Charles Hopkinson, Clare Leighton, and Henry McCarter. Also found are holiday cards to and from Edith Emerson.
  Business letters typically concern job details, sales of artwork, or art related events. Of note are referral letters from McCall Magazine editors and letters between the Philadlphia Art Alliance concerning Mr. Bart Tourison's housing projects. There are handwritten notes by Edith Emerson on a few of the letters.
  - Personal Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Letters, 1919-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
  - Business Letters, 1916-1922 (Box 1, Folder 9-14)
  - Oversize Christmas Cards from Berta and Elmer Hader, 1916-1965 (Box 3)
- Writings and Notes, 1887-1970; Series 3; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains writings and notes by Edith Emerson and others. Found here are an address book; a journal by Emerson's cousin, Mary Ingham, describing trips to Italy, Yellowstone, Holland, France, Germany, and Canada; an incomplete journal concerning travel to Great Britain and Germany; and notes on painting by Huger Elliott. Also found are a list of students at the Pennsylvania Museum School, a record of Emerson's exhibitions (1937-1970), and a manuscript "Cogslea Chronicles." Miscellaneous writings include a brief manuscript "Tales of Francis Joseph Fitz-Patrick."
  - Address Book and Notebook Listing Books Read, 1887-1900; undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Travel Journals, 1897-1903; 1928 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notebook of Travel Expenses, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Notes by Huger Elliott, 1921-1925 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - List of Students at Pennsylvania Museum School, 1929-1933 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Record Notebook, 1937-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Material Inserted in Exhibition Record Notebook, 1937-1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Notes on Artists, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Cogslea Chronicles", 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Artwork, 1882-1954; 1839; Series 4; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, OV 3
  Within this series is artwork, mainly paintings and drawings, by Edith Emerson and others. Included are 33 drawings and three annotated sketchbooks by Emerson, including one of India; a painting by Jessie Arms Botke; and prints by John H. Beatty, Anna Lea Merritt, and others.
  - Annotated Sketchbook, 1919-1926 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Annotated Sketchbook: "Journey to India", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Annotated Sketchbook, 1943-1954 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Loose Drawings Inserted in Annotated Sketchbook, 1943-1954 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Painting by Jessie Arms Botke, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Artwork by Others, 1839; 1882-1912 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Oversize Drawings (Box 3)
- Subject Files, circa 1865-1955; Series 5; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Subject files were maintained by Edith Emerson. Files may contain letters, notes, photographs, and printed material. Of note are subject files on Cecilia Beaux, Elizabeth Shippen Green Elliott, Thornton Oakley, Ruth St. Denis, the Moorestown Trust Company, the Philadelphia Art Alliance, "Song of Roland" illustrations, the WPA Women's Activities Division, the Writers and Illustrators Exchange, and other topics.
  - Agnes Irwin School, 1920-1950 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - American Architecture, circa 1894-1940 (Box 1, Folder 33-35)
  - Beaux Arts Institute of Design, Philadelphia Atelier of Mural Painting, 1932-1939 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Cecilia Beaux, 1930-1942 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Alison Mason Kingsbury Bishop, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Margaret Hittle Chapin, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Cosmopolitan Club, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Elizabeth Shippen Green Elliott, 1865-1954 (Box 1, Folder 41-45)
  - Berta and Elmer Hader, 1937-1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bertha E. Jaques, 1923-1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Elsa Laubach Jemne, 1916-1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rockwell Kent, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Charles Z. Klauder, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lake George- "Sylviana", 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. Ferris J. Meigs, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mexico, 1929-1943 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Mildred Stern Miller, 1911-1931 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Moorestown Trust Co., 1925-1927 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Musical Instruments, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Gertrude Norman, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Thornton Oakley, 1933-1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1924-1939 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Philadelphia "Art Notes" (For American Magazine of Arts), 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Katharine Rhoades, 1931-1935 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Song of Roland" Illustrations, circa 1938-1940s (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Ruth St. Denis, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Treasury Department: Painting and Sculpture, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Edward Warwick, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rebecca Whelan, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Works Progress Administration, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Writers and Illustrators Exchange, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Zettler Studios, N.Y. (Stained Glass), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Photographs, circa 1900-1971; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Found in this series are photographs of Edith Emerson and her friends, including a few with Violet Oakley. Also found are photographs of Emerson's family, photographs from a Mexico trip, interior views of her home and studio in Cogslea, works of art by Emerson, photographs of child models, and works of art by others.
  - Edith Emerson and Friends, circa 1915-1930s (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Emerson Family, 1921; 1932-1971 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Cogslea Interiors, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Mexico Trip, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Model, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Children, circa 1900-1930 (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
  - Sundial Mural, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Works of Art, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 38-40)
  - Works of Art by Others, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Negatives of Works of Art, circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Printed Material, circa 1916-1981; Series 7; 6 Folders Box 2
  Printed materials include brochures; clippings documenting Emerson's career; exhibition announcements and catalogs for Emerson, Violet Oakley, and others; as well as other miscellaneous published items and printed reproductions of her work.
  - Brochures, 1921-1941 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Clippings, circa 1916-1981; undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Exhibition Catalogs for Emerson/Oakley, 1923-1969 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Reproduction of Art Work, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous, 1919-1924 (Box 2, Folder 48)